Research Interests

Privacy, Federated Learning & AutoML: My primary focus is on learning, designing and building privacy-preserving federated systems and automated learning systems. My current research interests include privacy-preserving Machine Learning, Federated Learning and AutoML. Some of my past interests include Wireless Communications (3G and 4G) and IoT.

Education

Aug. 2018 - May 2023W. Lafayette, IN

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

- Advised by Prof. Xiaojun Lin
- Major GPA: 3.6/4.0

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

Hyderabad, India

B.Tech (WITH HONORS) IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

- · Advised by Prof. Bheemarjuna Reddy
- Major GPA: 8.88/10

Honors & Awards

2020	Invited Talk & Top 5% Paper, NeurIPS Pre-Registration Workshop	USA
2020	Graduate Research Assistantship, SuperPower Group, Psychological Sciences, Purdue	Indiana, USA
2017	Two-Year Graduate Teaching Assistantship, Electrical and Computer Engineering Department, Purdue	Indiana, U.S.A
2018	Winner and World Finalist for Emergensor Startup, Microsoft Imagine Cup, Japan National Final	Tokyo, Japan
2018	Winner, Third Business Plan Competition, University of Tokyo	Tokyo, Japan
2017	India-Japan Engineering Program Research Scholarship, University of Tokyo	Tokyo, Japan
2016	Undergraduate Teaching Assistantship, IIT Hyderabad	India
2016	Special Recognition & 8 th Rank for Young Team, IEEE Signal Processing Cup	India
2014	Academic Excellence Award, IIT Hyderabad	India
2010	Recipient of the prestigious National Talent Search Examination (N.T.S.E), Govt. of India	India

Publications

Rakshit Naidu, Harshita Diddee, Ajinkya Mulay, Aleti Vardhan, Krithika Ramesh, Ahmed Zamzam, "Towards Quantifying the Carbon Emissions of Differentially Private Machine Learning"

OpenMined

ICML 2021 SRML WORKSHOP

Ajinkya Mulay, Tushar Semwal, Ayush Agrawal, "FedPerf: A Practitioners' Guide to Performance of Federated Learning Algorithms"

OpenMined

NEURIPS 2020 Pre-REGISTRATION EXPERIMENT WORKSHOP

Ajinkya Mulay, Anand Basawade, Bheemarjuna Tamma, Anthony Franklin, "DFC: Dynamic UL-DL Frame Configuration for Improving Channel Access in eLAA"

NeWS Lab, IIT Hyderabaa

IEEE NETWORKING LETTERS

Ajinkya Mulay, Hideya Ochiai, Hiroshi Esaki, "IoT WebSocket Connection Management Algorithm for Early Warning Earthquake Alert Applications"

Esaki Lab, University of Tokyo

ACM/IEEE UCC, AUSTIN, TX, USA

Konkimalla Chandra Prakash, et. al., "A Novel Electric Network Frequency Classification Algorithm and an Electrical Power Signal Measurement Circuit"

LFOVIA Group, IIT Hyderabad

IEEE SIGNAL PROCESSING CUP, 2016

Pre-Prints

ARXIV, 2022

Skills

Focus Topics: Differential Privacy, Federated Learning, Graph Algorithms, AutoML **Machine Learning** PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, Pytorch-Lightning, Scikit-Learn, PySyft

Data AnalyticsPandas, Numpy, MatplotlibProgrammingPython, Cpp, R, Go, MATLAB, ŁTEXMobileSwift, Dart, Flutter, XCodeDevOpsAWS, Azure, Docker

Languages English (Proficient), Japanese (Basic), Hindi, Marathi

Experience

May 2021 - Aug 2021 Menlo Park, CA

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Developed a fast and highly scalable differentially private machine learning algorithm which outperforms the state-of-the-art model's test performance by 15%.
- · Implemented additional visualizations to improve gradient flow and easily debug larger machine learning runs.
- Technology Stack: Python, PyTorch

Aug. 2020 - Present West Lafayette, IN, USA

MACHINE LEARNING TEAM LEAD

Aug. 2020 - Present

- Designed algorithms to examine effects of parameter uncertainty on statistical power and identify regions of robustness/reactivity in specified
 parameter values over a high-dimensional parameter space
- Reduced inference, training time and resource usage to under 10% of the baseline with feature engineering while maintaining majority of the
 predictive capabilities
- Technology Stack: Python, PyTorch, Matplotlib, Pandas, Weights and Biases, R, Jupyter Notebooks, Git

Mar. 2020 - Present

Remote, USA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Mar. 2020 - Present

- Developing methods to characterize Private Federated Learning Systems and identify and track the performance of Federated Algorithms over varied environments with a single easy-to-use metric; proposal accepted at Pre-registration Workshop, NeurIPS 2020
- · Demonstrated top 5 Federated Machine Learning algorithms on 100+ virtual mobile devices with an accuracy of over 99% on LEAF datasets
- Technology Stack: PyTorch, Weights and Biases, PySyft, Matplotlib

Aug. 2018 - Mar. 2020West Lafayette, IN, USA

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

Aug. 2018 - Mar. 2020

Mentored 350+ undergraduate students and 15+ undergraduate teaching assistants to develop a strong fundamental understanding of electrical
engineering concepts

Aug. 2017 - Apr. 2018 *Hyderabad, India*

Undergraduate Student Researcher

Aug. 2017 - Apr. 2018

Jul. 2017 - Dec. 2018

- Designed and developed an algorithm to reduce interference between eLAA-WiFi networks by 40% using Game Theory techniques
- Technology Stack: MATLAB, Python

Jul. 2017 - Dec. 2018 Tokyo, Japan

• Built and maintained the back-end for a mobile application used to notify people of local emergencies

- Built and maintained the back-end for a mobile application used to notify people
 Reduced the map's refresh time by 60% to improve user experience
- Technology Stack: Azure, Java, Google Maps API, Android Studio, Go, Python

May 2017 - Jul. 2017Tokyo, Japan

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP

CHIEF SERVER ENGINEER

May 2017 - Jul. 2017

- Slashed the packet drop rate over a 3G IoT-Cloud network by 99% by designing a dynamic ping-pong connection management algorithm
- Technology Stack: Go, Arduino, C

May 2015 - Jul. 2016 Hyderabad, India

Undergraduate Student Researcher

May 2015 - Jul. 2016

- Developed a novel Neural Network-based classification algorithm to predict location of an audio recording using the Electrical Network Frequency (ENF) signature embedded in the audio file; achieved an accuracy of over 85%
- Technology Stack: MATLAB, Python

Teaching and Mentoring

MENTORING STUDENTS FOR ANVIL Jan 2022 - May 2022

Mentoring Undergraduate Students for the Anvil's Co-Founder AI Matching Platform Development

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR ECE 27000

Teaching assistant for Introduction to Digital Design

ection to Digital Design

Aug 2019 - May 2020

Aug 2018 - May 2019

Graduate Teaching Assistant for ECE 20002
Teaching assistant for Electrical Engineering Fundamentals II

Other Services

2022 **Reviewer**, Conference on Health, Inference, and Learning (CHIL)

Extra-Curricular_

2020-21 Active Blogger, Topics- Machine Learning, Differential Privacy, MS/PhD Applications

- 2018-21 Active Member, HKN (Eta Kappa Nau), Purdue University
- 2020-21 Active Member, Startup Purdue, Co-Founded Happyou, a mental health SaaS startup
- 2014-18 Soccer Member, Varsity Team, Inter & Intra-Collegiate Events, IIT Hyderabad
- 2015-17 **Head of Finance**, ELAN, IIT Hyderabad's Techno-Cultural Fest, managed budget in excess of \$40K
- 2015-17 **Events and Workshop Manager**, Entrepreneurship Cell, IIT Hyderabad